Finding aid to the Jean Struven Harris papers SSC.MS.00184
Sophia Smith Collection
Jean Struven Harris papers
1973-2005
1980-1993
Sophia Smith Collection
Harris, Jean (Jean Struven)
SSC.MS.00184
50 boxes (62.5 linear feet)
Teacher; Headmistress of Madeira School; Prison reformer. While incarcerated in the Bedford Hills Correctional Facility, N.Y. (1981-93) for the murder in the 1980 death of Herman Tarnower she worked in the Children's Center, and published three books: Stranger in Two Worlds (1986), They Always Call Us Ladies (1988), and Marking Time (1991) as well as a number of articles and unpublished manuscripts about women in prison. In 1986 she helped establish the Children of Bedford Fund. The papers primarily date from 1980 and consist of correspondence; clippings; printed material; research material on correctional systems; writings; legal documents; memorabilia; audiotapes; video tapes (of television interviews); and her trial record.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advancenotice.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may bedifficult to use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Jean Struven Harris donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1984 to 2015. The accession numbers are 84-32, 84-63, 85-3, 85S-39, 85S-47, 85S-78, 86S-17, 86S-50, 86S-88, 86S-92, 86S-110, 87S-4, 87S-23, 87S-78, 87S-102, 88S-33, 88S-85, 89S-8, 90S-1, 91S-75, 93S-14, 93S-15, 93S-55, 95S-8, 95S-23, 05S-30, 14S-08, 14S-17, 15S-59.
Biographical / Historical
Jean Struven was born in Chicago, IL, in 1923. She earned an A.B. from Smith College in 1945 and married James Harris in 1946. They had two sons, David and James, Jr. From 1947-50 and 1953- 66 Harris taught at a variety of primary and secondary levels at the Grosse Point (MI) Country Day School. In 1965, Harris completed her M.Ed. from [?] and divorced her husband. She moved to Chestnut Hill, PA, where she served as director of the Middle School at the Springside School from 1966-71. In 1966 she met and began an affair with Dr. Herman Tarnower. In 1971 she became headmistress of the Thomas School in Rowayton, CT and in 1976, Headmistress, Madeira School, McLean, VA. Harris was convicted of second-degree murder in the 1980 death of Herman Tarnower and incarcerated in the Bedford Hills Correctional Facility, N.Y., 1981-93. While in prison, she worked in the Children's Center, and wrote Stranger in Two Worlds (1986), They Always Call Us Ladies (1988), and Marking Time (1991) as well as a number of articles and unpublished manuscripts about women in prison. In 1986 she helped establish the Children of Bedford Fund, which pays school tuition for children whose mother's are incarcerated. After her release from prison Mrs. Harris worked for the Children of Bedford Fund and continued to write. Jean Harris died on December 23, 2012.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Additional materials are described in unpublished lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Related Materials
Associated material in Jean Harris Defense Fund and Committee Records.
Scope and Contents
The Jean Harris Papers consist of correspondence; clippings; printed material; research material on correctional systems; writings; legal documents; memorabilia; audiotapes; video tapes (of television interviews); and her trial record. The vast majority of the materials date from 1980.
Murder -- New York (State); Women prisoners -- United States -- History -- Sources; Children of women prisoners -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Law -- United States -- History -- 20th century; correspondence; Ephemera; Research; Manuscripts; Proofs; Legal documents; memorabilia; Audiotapes; Videotapes; Interviews; Bedford Hills Correctional Facility (N.Y.); Harris, Jean (Jean Struven); Tarnower, Herman; Harris, Jean Struven; Harris, Jean Struven
- Correspondence from supporters, writings and other materials pertaining to Tarnower murder, legal disputes, prison experience, 1980-1990; 2005-S-0030; 1.25 linear feet
  Lacey, Alice
  - Photographs of Jean Harris, 1987; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1993; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Annotated police, autopsy reports regarding Tarnower murder, 1980; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Magazines containing articles by Harris, 1993-1997; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - News clippings, 1986-1996; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Notes and reports including police disciplinary hearing, 1986-1989; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Women and mothers in prison: articles, clippings, correspondence, 1989-1990; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Documents regarding disputes over Harris' books, 1986-1989; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
  - Research notecards: women in prison, undated; 2005-S-0030 (Box 1)
- Jean Harris Annotated transcripts, VHS tapes, newspaper clippings, and correspondence, 1980-2005; 2014-S-0008; 2.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Annotated transcript: People v. Jean S. Harris, volume 3, 5-8, 1980; 2014-S-0008 (Box 1)
  - Annotated transcript: People v. Jean S. Harris, volumes 9-12, 14-16, 1980; 2014-S-0008 (Box 2)
  - VHS: Jean Harris interview with Barbara Walters, 1984; 2014-S-0008 (Box 2)
  - VHS: Interview with Kristi Witker, 1986; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: Interview, Oprah Winfrey Show, 1988; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: "A Current Affair," with Jean Harris, 1989; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: Interview with Barbara Walters, "20/20", 1993; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: Interview with Katie Couric, "Today Show", 1993; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: Interview with Charlie Gibson, "Good Morning America", 1994; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - VHS: Interview with Larry King, 1994; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Transcript: "Mr. Bolen Takes a Stand", 1981; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Appendix to brief of defendant-appellant: The People of the State of New York v. Jean S, Harris, 1981; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - "Dear All" letters, 1982-1983; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper, magazine clippings regarding Tarnower murder trial, 1980-1986; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper, magazine articles related to clemency and release, 1992-1994; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Jean Harris to Diane Miller, 1985-1986; 1997; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)
  - Material related to Smith College Class of 1945 40th, 50th reunions, undated; 2014-S-0014 (Box 3)
  - Children of Bedford records, 1986-2005; 2014-S-0008 (Box 3)